<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- I am using "true" as a way of citing clear 'loss of autonomy' or 'isolation'.-->
<root>
    <meta>
    <line nu="230">Of all creatures that have life and reason</line>
    <line nu="231"><shame>we women are the sorriest lot</shame></line>
    <line nu="232">first we must at a great expenditure of money</line>
    <line nu="233"><autonomy loss="true">buy a husband and even take on a master</autonomy></line>
    <line nu="234">over our body: this evil is more galling than the first.</line>
    <line nu="235"><patriarchy purchase_woman="true">Here is the most challenging contest, whether we will get a bad man</patriarchy></line>
    <line nu="236">or a good one.<marriage non_consensual="implied">Besides, divorce is unsavory</marriage></line>
    <line nu="237"><autonomy los="true">for a woman and it is not possible to say no to one's husband.</autonomy></line>
    <line nu="238">And when she comes into new customs and rules</line>
    <line nu="239"><family>a woman must be a prophet of what she could never learn at home:</family></line>
    <line nu="240"><motherhood birth="implied">how best to deal with her marriage partner;</motherhood></line>
    <line nu="241">and if we get it worked out well and a husband shares</line>
    <line nu="242">our life with us, and<violence domestic="avoided">he bears the yoke without violence,</violence></line>
    <line nu="243"><autonomy gain="conditional">life is to be envied. Otherwise we are better off dead.</autonomy></line>
    <line nu="244"><patriarchy faithfulnes="double-standard">But the man, when he is bored with things at home</patriarchy></line>
    <line nu="245">he can go out to ease the weariness of his heart.</line>
    <line nu="246"><alone isolated="true">But we have just one person to look to.</alone></line>
    <line nu="247"><motherhood birth="idealized">They say that we live a life free of danger</motherhood></line>
    <line nu="248">at home while they face battle with the spear.</line>
    <line nu="249"><autonomy gain="defiant">How wrong they are. I would rather stand three times</autonomy></line>
    <line nu="250"><motherhood birth="burdensome">in the line of battle than once bear a child.</motherhood></line>
<!-- The translator of this text extends Medea's rich monologue further. 
     This is important to include! -->
    <line nu="251"><autonomy loss="contrast">But the same story does not apply to you and me.</autonomy></line>
    <line nu="252"><patriarchy privilege="male">You have this city and your father's home,</patriarchy></line>
    <line nu="253">enjoyment of life, and the companionship of friends,</line>
    <line nu="254"><alone isolated="true" alienated="true">but, alone and without a city,</alone> I am abused</line>
    <line nu="255"><violence domestic="true">by my husband, carried off as plunder from a foreign land,</violence></line>
    <line nu="256"><alone isolated="true">I have no mother, no brother, no relative</alone></line>
    <line nu="257"><alone alienated="true">to offer me a safe haven from this disaster.</alone></line>
  
<!-- Copyright -->
  This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 2.5 License.
    </meta>
</root>
