
<root>
    <line nu="230">Of all things with life and understanding, [230]</line>
    <line>we women are the most unfortunate. </line>
    <line>First, we need a husband, someone we get </line>
    <line>for an excessive price. He then becomes </line>
    <line>the ruler of our bodies. And this misfortune </line>
    <line>adds still more troubles to the grief we have. </line>
    <line>Then comes the crucial struggle: this husband </line>
    <line>we have selected, is he good or bad? 270 </line>
    <line>For a divorce loses women all respect, </line>
    <line>yet we can’t refuse to take a husband. </line>
    <line>Then, when she goes into her husband’s home, </line>
    <line>with its new rules and different customs, </line>
    <line>she needs a prophet’s skill to sort out the man </line>
    <line nu="240">whose bed she shares. She can’t learn that at home. [240]</line>
    <line>Once we’ve worked hard at this, and with success, </line>
    <line>our husband accepts the marriage yoke </line>
    <line>and lives in peace—an enviable life. </line>
    <line>But if the marriage doesn’t work, then death 280 </line>
    <line>is much to be preferred. When the man tires </line>
    <line>of the company he keeps at home, he leaves, </line>
    <line>seeking relief for his distress elsewhere, </line>
    <line>outside the home. He gets his satisfaction </line>
    <line>with some male friend or someone his own age. </line>
    <line>We women have to look at just one man. </line>
    <line>Men tell us we live safe and secure at home, </line>
    <line>while they must go to battle with their spears. </line>
    <line>How stupid they are! I’d rather stand there </line>
    <line nu="250">three times in battle holding up my shield 290 [250]</line>
    <line>than give birth once. But your story and mine </line>
    <line>are not the same. For you have a city, </line>
    <line>you have your father’s house, enjoy your life </line>
    <line>with friends for company. But I’m alone. </line>
    <line>I have no city, and I’m being abused </line>
    <line>by my own husband. I was carried off, </line>
    <line>a trophy from a barbarian land. </line>
    <line>I have no mother, brother, or relation </line>
    <line>to shelter with in this extremity. </line>
    <line>And so I want to ask something from you. </line>
</root>
