
<GetPassage xmlns="http://chs.harvard.edu/xmlns/cts">
    <request>
        <requestName>GetPassage</requestName>
        <requestUrn>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2:265-325</requestUrn>
    </request>
    <reply>
        <urn>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2:265-325</urn>
        <passage>
            <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:py="http://codespeak.net/lxml/objectify/pytype" py:pytype="TREE">
                <text xml:lang="eng">
                    <body>
                        <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
                            <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                                <sp>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="265">yet in the moment she finds her honour wronged, no heart is filled with deadlier thoughts than hers.</l>
                                </sp>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="267">This will I do; for thou wilt be taking a just vengeance on thy husband, Medea. That thou shouldst mourn thy lot surprises me not. But lo! I see Creon, king of this land coming hither, </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="270">to announce some new resolve.</l>
                                </sp>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="271">Hark thee, Medea, I bid thee take those sullen looks and angry thoughts against thy husband forth from this land in exile, and with thee take both thy children and that without delay, for I am judge in this sentence, </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="275">and I will not return unto my house till I banish thee beyond the borders of the land.</l>
                                </sp>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Medea</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="277">Ah, me! now is utter destruction come upon me, unhappy that I am! For my enemies are bearing down on me full sail, nor have I any landing-place to come at in my trouble. </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="280">Yet for all my wretched plight I will ask thee, Creon, wherefore dost thou drive me from the land?</l>
                                </sp>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="282">I fear thee,—no longer need I veil my dread ’neath words,—lest thou devise against my child some cureless ill. Many things contribute to this fear of mine; </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="285">
                                        thou art a witch by nature, expert in countless sorceries, and thou art
                                        <pb xml:id="p.41"/>
                                        chafing for the loss of thy husband’s affection. I hear, too, so they tell me, that thou dost threaten the father of the bride, her husband, and herself with some mischief; wherefore I will take precautions ere our troubles come.
                                    </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="290">For ’tis better for me to incur thy hatred now, lady, than to soften my heart and bitterly repent it hereafter.</l>
                                </sp>
                                <milestone n="292" unit="card" resp="perseus"/>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Medea</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="292">Alas! this is not now the first time, but oft before, O Creon, hath my reputation injured me and caused sore mischief. Wherefore whoso is wise in his generation ought </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="295">never to have his children taught to be too clever; for besides the reputation they get for idleness, they purchase bitter odium from the citizens. For if thou shouldst import new learning amongst dullards, thou will be thought a useless trifler, void of knowledge; </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="300">
                                        while if thy fame in the city o’ertops that of the pretenders to cunning knowledge, thou wilt win their dislike. I too myself share in this ill-luck. Some think me clever and hate me,
                                        <del>others say I am too reserved, and some the very reverse</del>
                                        ;
                                        <note resp="editor">This line is inclosed by most editors in brackets as an interpolation from 808 below, where it is in place.</note>
                                    </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="305">others find me hard to please and not so very clever after all. Be that as it may, thou dost fear me lest I bring on thee something to mar thy harmony. Fear me not, Creon, ray position scarce is such that I should seek to quarrel with princes. Why should I, for how hast thou injured me? Thou hast betrothed thy daughter </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="310">where thy fancy prompted thee. No, ’tis my husband I hate, though I doubt not thou hast acted wisely herein. And now I grudge not thy prosperity; betroth thy child, good luck to thee, but let me abide in this land, for though I have been wronged </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="315">I will be still and yield to my superiors.</l>
                                </sp>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="316">Thy words are soft to hear, but much I dread lest thou art devising some mischief in thy heart, and less than ever do I trust thee now; for a cunning woman, and man likewise, </l>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" n="320">
                                        is easier to guard against when quick-tempered
                                        <pb xml:id="p.42"/>
                                        than when taciturn. Nay, begone at once! speak me no speeches, for this is decreed, nor hast thou any art whereby thou shalt abide amongst us, since thou hatest me.
                                    </l>
                                </sp>
                                <milestone n="324" unit="card" resp="perseus"/>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Medea</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="324">O, say not so! by thy knees and by thy daughter newly-wed, I do implore!</l>
                                </sp>
                                <sp>
                                    <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                                    <l xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0006.tlg003.perseus-eng2" resp="perseus" rend="indent" n="325">Thou wastest words; thou wilt never persuade me.</l>
                                </sp>
                            </div>
                        </div>
                    </body>
                </text>
            </TEI>
        </passage>
    </reply>
</GetPassage>
