<root>
    <line nu="230">Of all things that have life and sense we </line>
    <line nu="231">women are the most hapless creatures; first </line>
    <line nu="232">must we <marriage>buy a husband</marriage> at an exorbitant </line>
    <line nu="233">price, and o’er ourselves a tyrant set which </line>
    <line nu="234">is an evil worse than the first; </line>
    <line nu="235">and herein lies the most important issue, </line>
    <line nu="236">whether our choice be good or bad. For </line>
    <line nu="237"><marriage>divorce is discreditable to women</marriage>, nor can </line>
    <line nu="238"> <patriarchy>we disown our lords.</patriarchy> Next must the wife, </line>
    <line  nu="239">coming as she does to ways and customs </line>
    <line nu="240">new, since she hath not learnt the lesson in </line>
    <line nu="241">her home, have a diviner’s eye </line>
    <line nu="242"> <patriarchy>to see how best to treat the partner of her life</patriarchy>. If </line>
    <line nu="243"><patriarchy>haply we perform these tasks with</patriarchy> </line>
    <line nu="244">thoroughness and tact, and the <marriage>husband</marriage> </line>
    <line nu="245">live with us, without resenting the yoke, our </line>
    <line nu="246"><marriage>life is a happy one;</marriage> if not, <violence suicide> twere best to die.</violence> </line>
    <line nu="247">But when a man is vexed with what he </line>
    <line nu="248">finds indoors, </line>
    <line nu="249"><violence>he goeth forth and rids his soul</violence> of its </line>
    <line nu="250">disgust, betaking him to some friend or </line>
    <line nu="251">comrade of like age; whilst we must needs </line>
    <line nu="252"> regard his single self. </line>
    <line nu="253">And yet they say we live secure at home, </line>
    <line nu="254">while they are at the <violence>wars</violence>, </line>
    <line nu="255">with their sorry reasoning, for I would </line>
    <line nu="256"><autonomy>gladly take my stand in battle array three</autonomy> </line>
    <line nu="257">times o’er, than once give </line>
    <line nu="258"><motherhood birth>birth</motherhood>. </line>
    <line nu="259">But enough! this language suits not thee as </line>
    <line nu="260">it does me; thou hast a city here, a <family>father’s</family> </line>
    <line nu="261">house, <autonomy>some joy in life, and friends to share</autonomy> </line>
    <line nu="262">thy thoughts, </line>
    <line nu="263"><alone isolated>but I am destitute, without a city</alone>, and </line>
    <line nu="264">therefore <marriage>scorned by my husband, a <alone isolated>captive</alone></marriage> </line>
    <line nu="265">I from a foreign shore, <family>with no mother</family>, </line>
    <line nu="266">brother, or kinsman in whom to find a new </line>
    <line nu="267">haven of refuge from this calamity. </line>
</root>
