<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text lang="en"><body><div1 type="Book" n="10" org="uniform" sample="complete"><milestone ed="p" unit="card" />
<p><milestone n="487" unit="line" />"And the goddess answered,
‘Odysseus, noble son of <placeName key="perseus,Laertes" authname="perseus,Laertes">Laertes</placeName>, you shall none of you stay here
any longer if you do not want to, but there is another journey which
you have got to take before you can sail homewards. You must go to
the house of Hades and of dread Persephone to consult the ghost
[<term lang="xgreek">psukhê</term>] of the blind Theban seer
[<term lang="xgreek">mantis</term>] Teiresias whose mind [<term lang="xgreek">phrenes</term>]
is still in place within him. To him alone has Persephone left his
consciousness [<term lang="xgreek">noos</term>] even in death, but the other
ghosts flit about aimlessly.’</p>

<p><milestone n="496" unit="line" />"I was dismayed when I heard
this. I sat up in bed and wept, and would gladly have lived no longer
to see the light of the sun, but presently when I was tired of
weeping and tossing myself about, I said, ‘And who shall guide
me upon this voyage - for the house of Hades is a port that no ship
can reach.’</p>

<p><milestone n="504" unit="line" />"‘You will want no
guide,’ she answered; ‘raise you mast, set your white
sails, sit quite still, and the North Wind will blow you there of
itself. When your ship has traversed the waters of Okeanos, you will
reach the fertile shore of Persephone's country with its groves
of tall poplars and willows that shed their fruit untimely; here
beach your ship upon the shore of Okeanos, and go straight on to the
dark abode of Hades. You will find it near the place where the rivers
Pyriphlegethon and Cocytus (which is a branch of the river Styx) flow
into Acheron, and you will see a rock near it, just where the two
roaring rivers run into one another.</p>

<p><milestone n="516" unit="line" />"‘When you have reached this
spot, as I now tell you, dig a trench a cubit or so in length,
breadth, and depth, and pour into it as a drink-offering to all the
dead, first, honey mixed with milk, then wine, and in the third place
water-sprinkling white barley meal over the whole. Moreover you must
offer many prayers to the poor feeble ghosts, and promise them that
when you get back to <placeName key="tgn,1007519" authname="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName> you will sacrifice a barren heifer to
them, the best you have, and will load the pyre with good things.
More particularly you must promise that Teiresias shall have a black
sheep all to himself, the finest in all your flocks.</p>

</div1></body></text></TEI.2>