<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI.2><text lang="en"><body><div1 type="Book" n="10" org="uniform" sample="complete"><milestone ed="p" unit="card" />
<p><milestone n="156" unit="line" />"When I had nearly got back to
the ship some god took pity upon my solitude, and sent a fine
antlered stag right into the middle of my path. He was coming down
his pasture in the forest to drink of the river, for the heat of the
sun drove him, and as he passed I struck him in the middle of the
back; the bronze point of the spear went clean through him, and he
lay groaning in the dust until the life went out of him. Then I set
my foot upon him, drew my spear from the wound, and laid it down; I
also gathered rough grass and rushes and twisted them into a fathom
or so of good stout rope, with which I bound the four feet of the
noble creature together; having so done I hung him round my neck and
walked back to the ship leaning upon my spear, for the stag was much
too big for me to be able to carry him on my shoulder, steadying him
with one hand. As I threw him down in front of the ship, I called the
men and spoke cheeringly man by man to each of them. ‘Look here
my friends,’ said I, ‘we are not going to die so much
before our time after all, and at any rate we will not starve so long
as we have got something to eat and drink on board.’ On this
they uncovered their heads upon the sea shore and admired the stag,
for he was indeed a splendid man. Then, when they had feasted their
eyes upon him sufficiently, they washed their hands and began to cook
him for dinner.</p>

<p><milestone n="183" unit="line" />"Thus through the livelong day to
the going down of the sun we stayed there eating and drinking our
fill, but when the sun went down and it came on dark, we camped upon
the sea shore. When the child of morning, fingered Dawn, appeared, I
called a council and said, ‘My friends, we are in very great
difficulties; listen therefore to me. We have no idea where the sun
either sets or rises, so that we do not even know East from West. I
see no way out of it; nevertheless, we must try and find one. We are
certainly on an island, for I went as high as I could this morning,
and saw the sea reaching all round it to the horizon; it lies low,
but towards the middle I saw smoke rising from out of a thick forest
of trees.’</p>

<p><milestone n="198" unit="line" />"Their hearts sank as they heard
me, for they remembered how they had been treated by the
Laestrygonian Antiphates, and by the savage ogre Polyphemus. They
wept bitterly in their dismay, but there was nothing to be got by
crying, so I divided them into two companies and set a leader over
each; I gave one company to Eurylokhos, while I took command of the
other myself. Then we cast lots in a helmet, and the lot fell upon
Eurylokhos; so he set out with his twenty-two men, and they wept, as
also did we who were left behind.</p>

<p><milestone n="210" unit="line" />"When they reached Circe's
house they found it built of cut stones, on a site that could be seen
from far, in the middle of the forest. There were wild mountain
wolves and lions prowling all round it - poor bewitched creatures
whom she had tamed by her enchantments and drugged into subjection.
They did not attack my men, but wagged their great tails, fawned upon
them, and rubbed their noses lovingly against them. As hounds crowd
round their master when they see him coming from dinner - for they
know he will bring them something - even so did these wolves and
lions with their great claws fawn upon my men, but the men were
terribly frightened at seeing such strange creatures. Presently they
reached the gates of the goddess’ house, and as they stood there
they could hear Circe within, singing most beautifully as she worked
at her loom, making a web so fine, so soft, and of such dazzling
colors as no one but a goddess could weave. On this Polites, whom I
valued and trusted more than any other of my men, said, ‘There
is some one inside working at a loom and singing most beautifully;
the whole place resounds with it, let us call her and see whether she
is woman or goddess.’</p>

</div1></body></text></TEI.2>